MINGZE WANG

210, Jingyuan Building #6, Peking University, Beijing, China, 100084 mingzewang@stu.pku.edu.cn

SHORT BIO

I am a fourth-year Ph.D candidate in Computational Mathematics, Peking University. I am very fortunate to be advised by Prof. Weinan E. Prior to that, I received my B.S. degree in Pure and Applied Mathematics (ranking 1/111 for the first three years during my undergraduate study) from Zhejiang University in 2021. My homepage is https://wmz9.github.io/.

EDUCATION

Peking University

Beijing, China

Ph.D Candidate, Computational Mathematics

2021.09 - Present

School of Mathematical Sciences

Advisor: Prof. Weinan E.

Zhejiang University

Hangzhou, China

Bachelor of Science, Pure and Applied Mathematics

2017.09 - 2021.06

School of Mathematical Sciences

Academic ranking: 1/111, Comprehensive ranking: 1/111, Major GPA: 4.84/5 (95.5/100).

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am broadly interested in theory, algorithm and application of machine learning. I am also interested in non-convex and convex optimization. Recently, I am also dedicated to use theory to design algorithms elegantly. Specifically, my recent research topics are

- Deep learning theory: theory and theory-inspired algorithm [1][2][3][4][5][6][8][9][10][11][12]
 - **Expressivity**: Explore the expressive power of Transformers through the lens of approximation theory [9][12]; the expressivity of state-space models.
 - **Optimization**: Why can optimization algorithms converge to global minima when training neural networks [2][4][12]?
 - **Implicit Bias**: Why can optimization algorithms converge to global minima with favorable generalization ability when training neural networks? Flat-minima-bias [3][5][9][10][11]; max-margin-bias aspects [4][6].
 - Generalization: How to measure the generalization ability of neural networks [1].
 - Algorithm Design: For machine learning problems, design new optimization algorithms which can (i) converge faster [10]; (ii) generalize better [6][10].
- Transformer and Large Language Models: theory and algorithm. [8][10][12]
 - **Expressivity**: The expressive power and mechanisms of Transformer [8][12]; the mechanisms of incontext learning [12]; the expressivity of state-space models.
 - Algorithm Design: Design faster optimizers for training LLMs [10]; design more efficient model architectures; design more efficient strategy for data selection.
- Non-convex and Convex Optimization: theory and algorithm. [2][4][6][10][11][12]
 - Convex Optimization in ML. [6]
 - Non-convex Optimization in ML. [2][4][10][11][12]
 - **Algorithm Design**: Design faster optimizers for training neural networks [10]; accelerate the convergence for the problems with specific structure [6].

• Computer vision and Natural language processing: algorithm and application [7].

PUBLICATIONS & PREPRINTS

- * indicates equal contribution.
- 12. Mingze Wang*, Ruoxi Yu*, Weinan E, Lei Wu. How Transformers Implement Induction Heads: Approximation and Optimization Analysis. Under review. arXiv preprint: 2410.11474, 1-39. 2024.
- 11. Zhanpeng Zhou*, Mingze Wang*, Yuchen Mao, Bingrui Li, Junchi Yan. Sharpness-Aware Minimization Efficiently Selects Flatter Minima Late in Training. Under review. arXiv preprint: 2410.10373, 1-24. 2024.
- 10. Mingze Wang, Jinbo Wang, Haotian He, Zilin Wang, Guanhua Huang, Feiyu Xiong, Zhiyu Li, Weinan E, Lei Wu. Improving Generalization and Convergence by Enhancing Implicit Regularization. Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2024), 1-35. 2024.
- 9. Liu Ziyin, Mingze Wang, Hongchao Li, Lei Wu. Loss Symmetry and Noise Equilibrium of Stochastic Gradient Descent. Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2024), 1-26. 2024.
- 8. Mingze Wang, Weinan E. Understanding the Expressive Power and Mechanisms of Transformer for Sequence Modeling. Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2024), 1-70. 2024.
- 7. Guanhua Huang, Yuchen Zhang, Zhe Li, Yongjian You, Mingze Wang, Zhouwang Yang. Are AI-Generated Text Detectors Robust to Adversarial Perturbations? Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, (ACL 2024), 1-20. 2024.
- 6. Mingze Wang, Zeping Min, Lei Wu. Achieving Margin Maximization Exponentially Fast via Progressive Norm Rescaling. International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML 2024), 1-38. 2023.
- 5. Mingze Wang, Lei Wu. A Theoretical Analysis of Noise Geometry in Stochastic Gradient Descent.

 NeurIPS 2023 Workshop on Mathematics of Modern Machine Learning (NeurIPS 2023 Workshop M3L).

 arXiv preprint: 2310.00692, 1-30. 2023.
- 4. Mingze Wang, Chao Ma. Understanding Multi-phase Optimization Dynamics and Rich Nonlinear Behaviors of ReLU Networks. Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2023, Spotlight (Top 3.5%)), 1-94. 2023.
- 3. Lei Wu, Mingze Wang, Weijie J. Su. The alignment property of SGD noise and how it helps select flat minima: A stability analysis. Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2022), 1-25. 2022.
- 2. Mingze Wang, Chao Ma. Early Stage Convergence and Global Convergence of Training Mildly Parameterized Neural Networks. Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2022), 1-73. 2022.
- 1. Mingze Wang, Chao Ma. Generalization Error Bounds for Deep Neural Networks Trained by SGD. Under review. arXiv preprint: 2206.03299, 1-32. 2022.

SERVICE

Conference: Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS); International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR); Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS).

Journal: Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR); Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI); Pattern Recognition (PR); Transactions on Machine Learning Research (TMLR); Journal of Machine Learning (JML).

SELECTED AWARDS & HONOURS

National Scholarship (top 2%; 30,000 RMB), The Ministry of Education.	2024.09
Principal Scholarship, Peking University.	2024.05
BICMR Mathematical Award for Graduate Students (top 1%; 110,000 RMB), Peking University.	2023.11
Schlumberge Scholarship (30,000 RMB), Peking University.	2022.10
PKU Academic Innovation Award (top 1%), Peking University.	2022.10
Outstanding Graduate of Zhejiang Province (top 5%); Outstanding Graduate of ZJU	2021.05
National Scholarship (top 2%)	2019.10
First Class Scholarship of ZJU (top 3%)	2019, 2020.10
Zhejiang Provincial Government Scholarship	2018.10
First Prize of Mathematical Contest in Modeling of ZJU (top 1%)	2020.06
Meritourious Award in The Mathematical Contest in Modeling	2020.02
National Second Prize of Chinese Undergraduate Mathematical Contest in Modeling (top 2.5%)	2019.10

EXPERIENCE

Peking University Beijing, China Teaching assistant: Deep Learning Theory, taught by Prof. Zhiyuan Li (TTIC) Summer School 2023. Teaching assistant: Calculus (A) Fall 2021

Teaching assistant: Calculus (B) Fall 2022, 2023; Spring 2022, 2023, 2024

Institute for Advanced Algorithms Research

Shanghai, China Algorithm Intern 2023.12 - 2024.08

Work on designing faster optimizers for pretraining large language models.

Moqi Technology Beijing, China Algorithm Intern 2021.09 - 2022.06